District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education 002
People's Archive, MLK Library
District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education (DCCBPE) Collection
1965-1982
People's Archive, MLK Library
D.C. Citizens for Better Public Education
002
7 Linear feet
15 Boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were donated to the Library by Miles Mark Fisher, IV, 1984 President of the District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education (DCCBPE).
Arrangement
Series 1: Office Files (1982-1983; 1.25LF): Contains office files maintained by DCCBPE covering annual meetings, board member meetings, copies of Energetic News, executive directors' reports, and various topical files.
Series 2: Special Education (1978-1983; 1.25LF): Contains fact sheets, plans, newsletters, legislation, publications, litigation, maps, agreements, and reports relating to special education in the District.
Series 3: Newsletters (1965-1982; 1.75LF): Contains copies of DCCBPE's newsletter, The Bulletin Board.
Series 4: Reports (1974-1976; 1.25LF): Consists of reports on decentralization, resource allocation, school lunch/breakfast programs, and student rights and responsibilities for D.C. schools. Of particular significance is a report prepared in 1974 titled A Quest for Educational Opportunity in a Major Urban School System: The Case of Washington DC, which was the result of a study conducted by the Educational Finance and Governance Center of Syracuse University under contract with DCCBPE.
Series 5: Directories and Handbooks (1973-1978; 1.25LF): Contains a directory of services for children with disabilities; guides on special education services, student assessment, and placement. Series also includes the 1977 edition of the D.C. Public School's Administrative Procedure Handbook.
Series 6: Publications (967-1979; 0.25LF): Consists mainly of monographs published by DCCBPE.
Biographical / Historical
The District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education (DCCBPE) was organized in 1964 to assess educational needs in the District and to lobby for educational improvements before the United States Congress and local government officials. DCCBPE's first public meeting was held on March 28, 1965 at Rankin Chapel on the campus of Howard University, with United States Attorney General Robert F. Kennedy as the keynote speaker. The organization was involved in many major issues affecting public education in the District during the 1960s and 1970s, including decentralization of the school superintendent's authority, de facto segregation, Home Rule efforts, and student rights. DCCBPE founded the Reading is Fundamental (RIF) program headed by Margaret McNamara (wife of Robert McNamara, Secretary of Defence) RIF provided free books to students and eventually spread nationwide giving away books to millions of children. DCCBPE also hosted an annual awards dinner, which honored persons who made exceptional contributions to public education. DCCBPE ceased operations in 1984.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains District of Columbia Citizens for Better Public Education (DCCBPE) annual and board of directors' meeting minutes, administrative directives, legislative testimony, financial reports, and copies of the organization's newsletter, the Bulletin Board. Other materials included are numerous studies and reports sponsored by DCCBPE including Student Responsibilities and Rights, A Quest for Educational Opportunity in a Major Urban School District, and Creating Resource Allocation System.
Education; Reading Is Fundamental, Inc.; Public schools; Associations, institutions, etc; People with disabilities; Special education
- Series 1: Office Files, 1982-1983
  Scope and Contents
  Contains office files maintained by DCCBPE covering annual meetings, board member meetings, copies of Energetic News, executive director's reports, and various topical files.
  - Board of director's meeting minutes and agenda, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of director's meeting minutes and agenda, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of director's meeting minutes and agenda, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of director's meeting minutes and agenda, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mercedes A. King, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mercedes A. King, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Director's reports, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Testimony, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual meeting working papers, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Statement on the fiscal year budget, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual meeting, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Capital Comprehensive Plan, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Conferences and meetings, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Education Coalition, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Handicapped hearings, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fiscal budget information, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Energetic News (Vols. 1-4), Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Special Education Workshop, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reading is Fundamental Committee report, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Learning disabilities, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Special Education, 1978-1983
  Contains fact sheets, plans, newsletters, legislation, publications, litigation, maps, agreements, and reports relating to special education in the District.
  - Residential placements, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Comprehensive plan for the Delivery of Services to the Handicapped Children and Youth, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Civil Action #16-77 - Children's Defense Fund, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes of Deborah Ramsey, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Children's Center, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Revised Agreement for Residential Placement, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Proposal Board of Education Rules - Special education of D.C., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Compliance monitoring branch information, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Information from Closer Look, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Comprehensive Plan, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Special Education meeting, 9/24/1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Special education complaint management system, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Department of Education News, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Development I.E.P. information, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Fact Sheet - special education, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Intensive Junior high school instruction - discussion paper only, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - WandS NSC - D. Ramsey information, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Annual program plan amendment - Education of the Handicapped Act, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Annual Program, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Special education memorandum of Agreement, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Special education monitoring and observation, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - D.C. Law 2-137 - Mentally Retarded Citizens Constitutional Rights and Dignity Act of 1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Overview of program administration, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Parent Involvement Committee Workshop - I.E.P., Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Parent Involvement Committee, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Quality monitoring - D.C.P.S., 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Referral process for Assessment identification, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Road Map to Special education for Handicapped Children, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Residential placement agreement, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Special education information, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Special education cases, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Draft FY 1981-83 State Plan for Part B of the Education of the Handicapped Act, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Special Education Fair, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Special Transfer form - Area A, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Who is Really Special?, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Task Force-Cedar Knoll Oak Hill, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Waddy decision testimony, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Workshop parent training, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Court hearing, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Newsletters, 1965-1982
  Contains DCCBPE's newsletter, The Bulletin Board from 1965-1982.
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin Board - April 1965-December (non-inclusive), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Special Report: Merit Pay Differential, December 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Special Report: Staffing: The Clark Plan, December 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), February 1971-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), February 1971-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), February 1971-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), February 1971-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), February 1971-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Invierno, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Special Report, January 1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), January 1976-October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), January 1976-October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), January 1976-October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Special Report, October 1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), December 1978-September 1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), December 1978-September 1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), December 1978-September 1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), December 1978-September 1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bulletin Board (non-inclusive), December 1978-September 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Parent Resource Paper, September 1979 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Reports, 1974-1976
  Consists of reports, some of which were sponsored by DCCBPE. Topics covered by the reports include decentralization, resource allocation, school lunch/breakfast programs, and student rights and responsibilities for D.C. schools. Of particular significance is a report prepared in 1974, titled A Quest for Educational Opportunity in a Major Urban School System: The Case of Washington, D.C. which was the result of a study conducted by the Educational Finance and Governance Center of Syracuse University under contract with DCCBPE.
  - Final draft: A Quest for Educational Opportunity in a Major Urban School System: The Case of Washington D.C., December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - A Quest for Educational Opportunity in a Major Urban School System: The Case of Washington D.C., August 1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Report on the School Lunch and Breakfast Programs in Washington D.C. by Marcy Gross, August 1975 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Equalization: A Report on Compliance with Two Court Decisions in the District of Columbia, June 1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Student Responsibilities and Rights: A Training Booklet, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Creating a Resource Allocation System for the D.C. Public Schools, January 1977 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Creating a Resource Allocation System for the D.C. Public Schools, April 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Series 5: Directories and Handbooks, 1973-1978
  This series contains a directory of services for handicapped children and guides regarding special education services and student assessment and placement. Also included is the 1977 edition of the D.C. Public School's Administrative Procedure Handbook prepared during Vincent Reed's tenure as School Superintendent.
  - Directory of Services for Handicapping Conditions, September 1973 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Directory of Services for Handicapping Conditions, September 1973 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Directory of Services for Handicapping Conditions, September 1973 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Directory of Services for Handicapping Conditions, September 1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Assessing Special Education: A Guide for Parents and Advocates, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Public Schools Central Administration Directory, 1976-1978 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Administrator's Guide to Student Identification, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Public Schools Administrative Procedure Handbook - Vincent E. Reed, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Public Schools Administrative Procedure Handbook - Vincent E. Reed, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Series 6: Publications, 1967-1979
  Consists mainly of monographs published by DCCBPE.
  - Toward Better Schools: A Summary of the Passow Report, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Early Education: School for Children Under Six, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Your School Record: Questions and Answers about a New Set of Rights for Parents and Students, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - What Every Teacher Should Know About Student Rights, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - A Handbook for Standardized School Testing: For Parents and Students, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Kendall Demonstration Elementary School - Gallaudet College, Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Minorities in Marine Education, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 8)